<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en"/>
                <principal>
                    <persName ref="#."/>
                </principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#."/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority/>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en">Attribution 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0) </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when-iso="...."/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title type="main"/>
                <title type="genre"/>
                <title type="topic"/>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier/>
                    <msContents/>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident=""/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when-iso="....-..-.." who="#.">Encoding of the text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="transcription">
                <pb n="" facs=".JPG"/>
                <p> ( 35 )<lb/> CHAPTER II.</p>
                <p rend="indent">Elizabeth had settled it that Mr.</p>
                <p rend="indent">Darcy would bring his sister to visit her,<lb/> the very day after her reaching Pember-<lb break="no"/>ley; and was
                    consequently resolved not<lb/> to be out of sight of the inn the whole of<lb/> that morning. But her conclusion was<lb/> false;
                    for on the very morning after<lb/> their own arrival at Lambton, these<lb/> visitors came. They had been walking<lb/> about the
                    place with some of their new<lb/> friends, and were just returned to the inn<lb/> to dress themselves for dining with the<lb/>
                    same family, when the sound of a car-<lb break="no"/>riage drew them to a window, and they<lb/> saw a gentleman and lady in a
                    curricle,<lb/> driving up the street. Elizabeth im-<lb break="no"/>mediately recognising the livery, guessed<lb/> what it meant,
                    and imparted no small<lb/> degree of surprise to her relations, by<lb/> acquainting them with the honour which<lb/> she<lb/> ( 36
                    )<lb/> she expected. Her uncle and aunt were<lb/> all amazement; and the embarrass-<lb break="no"/>ment of her manner as she
                    spoke, joined<lb/> to the circumstance itself, and many of<lb/> the circumstances of the preceding day,<lb/> opened to them a new
                    idea on the busi-<lb break="no"/>ness. Nothing had ever suggested it<lb/> before, but they now felt that there was<lb/> no other
                    way of accounting for such at-<lb break="no"/>tentions from such a quarter, than by<lb/> supposing a partiality for their
                    niece.</p>
                <p rend="indent">While these newly-born notions were<lb/> passing in their heads, the perturbation<lb/> of Elizabeth's feelings was
                    every moment<lb/> increasing. She was quite amazed at<lb/> her own discomposure; but amongst<lb/> other causes of disquiet, she
                    dreaded lest<lb/> the partiality of the brother should have<lb/> said too much in her favour; and more<lb/> than commonly anxious
                    to please, she<lb/> naturally suspected that every power of<lb/> pleasing would fail her. <lb/> She retreated from the window,
                        fear-<lb break="no"/>ful<lb/> ( 37 )<lb/> ful of being seen; and as she walked up<lb/> and down the room, endeavouring to<lb/>
                    compose herself, saw such looks of en-<lb break="no"/>quiring surprise in her uncle and aunt,<lb/> as made every thing worse.
                    <lb/> Miss Darcy and her brother appeared,<lb/> and this formidable introduction took<lb/> place. With astonishment did
                    Elizabeth<lb/> see, that her new acquaintance was at<lb/> least as much embarrassed as herself.</p>
                <p rend="indent">Since her being at Lambton, she had h<lb/> eard that Miss Darcy was exceedingly<lb/> proud; but the observation of a
                    very<lb/> few minutes convinced her, that she was<lb/> only exceedingly shy. She found it<lb/> difficult to obtain even a word
                    from her<lb/> beyond a monosyllable. <lb/> Miss Darcy was tall, and on a larger<lb/> scale than Elizabeth; and, though little<lb/>
                    more than sixteen, her figure was formed,<lb/> and her appearance womanly and grace-<lb break="no"/>ful. She was less handsome
                    than her<lb/> brother, but there was sense and good<lb/> humour<lb/> ( 38 )<lb/> humour in her face, and her manners<lb/> were
                    perfectly unassuming and gentle.</p>
                <p rend="indent">Elizabeth, who had expected to find in<lb/> her as acute and unembarrassed an ob-<lb break="no"/>server as ever Mr.
                    Darcy had been, was<lb/> much relieved by discerning such dif-<lb break="no"/>ferent feelings. <lb/> They had not been long
                    together,<lb/> before Darcy told her that Bingley was<lb/> also coming to wait on her; and she had<lb/> barely time to express her
                    satisfaction,<lb/> and prepare for such a visitor, when<lb/> Bingley's quick step was heard on the<lb/> stairs, and in a moment he
                    entered the<lb/> room. All Elizabeth's anger against him<lb/> had been long done away; but, had she<lb/> still felt any, it could
                    hardly have stood<lb/> its ground against the unaffected cor-<lb break="no"/>diality with which he expressed himself,<lb/> on
                    seeing her again. He enquired in a<lb/> friendly, though general way, after her<lb/> family, and looked and spoke with the<lb/>
                    same good-humoured ease that he had<lb/> ever done.</p>
                <p rend="indent">To </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
